Finding Aid for Stevens Thomson Mason Papers, 1827-1842
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Stevens Thomson Mason Papers
1827-1842
Mason, Stevens Thomson, 1811-1843.
851813 Aa 2
First governor of Michigan; correspondence, drafts of letters to Andrew Jackson and to Secretary of State John Forsyth; draft of his inaugural address, 1838 and of other messages to the Legislature; topics covered include the Toledo War and the dispute arising from his appointment as Secretary of the Michigan Territory.
0.6 linear feet in 2 boxes
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The major portion of the Mason papers came from Charles Hemans (donor no. 3848 ) and came to the library in 1961. Other materials came from Peter Bailey (donor no 1687 ) and Augustus Hendelman (donor no. 2823 )
The collection is open to research.
Stevens Thomson Mason was born in Virginia (October 27, 1811) and educated in Kentucky where his father had emigrated in 1812. In 1830, his father, John Mason, was appointed secretary of the Territory of Michigan by President Andrew Jackson. He resigned a year later and left for Texas and Mexico perhaps on a mission for the president. In his place, Jackson named the nineteen year old Stevens Mason to the vacant secretariat, taking his oath of office on July 25, 1831. As secretary Mason was also ex-officio governor during the absence of then Governor Porter. With Porter's death, July 6, 1834, Mason became acting governor. Here he led the movement for statehood and prosecuted the boundary dispute with Ohio. He was elected governor in his own right on November 3, 1835, serving two terms, leaving office on January 7, 1840. His administration was plagued by financial difficulties brought on by the Panic of 1837 bringing to a halt many internal improvements projects that had been anticipated. Mason did not run for a third term, instead retired from politics, moving to New York where he practiced law. He died January 4, 1843.
The Mason papers include correspondence, drafts of letters to Andrew Jackson and to Secretary of State John Forsyth; draft of his inaugural address, 1838 and of other messages to the Legislature; topics covered include the Toledo War and the dispute arising from his appointment as Secretary of the Michigan Territory. The Mason papers have been arranged into three series: Correspondence (covering the years 1831-1842); Other papers; and Addresses and messages to the Legislature in the period of 1834 to 1840.
Subjects:
Indians of North America--Michigan.; Mason, Stevens Thomson, 1811-1843.; Michigan--Boundaries--Ohio.; Michigan--History.; Ohio--Boundaries--Michigan.; University of Michigan. Library.; Governors--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Detroit (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Dwellings--Michigan--Detroit.; Mason, Emily Virginia.; Mason, Stevens Thomson, 1811-1843.; Sculpture.; Wright, Dorothea Mason.
Contributors:
Cass, Lewis, 1782-1866.; Norvell, John, 1789-1850.; Owen, George W.; Vail, Aaron.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Prints.
- Correspondence
  (includes both originals and photostatic copies)
  - August 1, 1831, original and typed copy (Box 1, Folder 1)
    (letter from Mason to Andrew Jackson referring to opposition to Mason's appointment as Secretary of Michigan Territory)
  - 1831
    - Notice from the secretary of the Detroit Athenaeum, R.L. Rice, of a meeting to be held November 1, 1831, October, 1831; photostat (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Letter of I. Barnes to Mason, December 20, 1831; photostat (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Stevens T. Mason to "The Senators of the U. States" concerning his appointment as Secretary of the Michigan Territory, 1831 undated; 3 pages photostat (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1832-1834
    - John Norvell to Stevens T. Mason, concerning Senate confirmation of Mason's appointment, May 24, 1832; photostat (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Lewis Cass to Stevens T. Mason, referring to Indian uprisings in the Northwest, May 31, 1832 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - A[ustin] E. Wing to Stevens T. Mason, informing Mason of confirmation of his appointment as Secretary of Michigan Territory, June 21, 1832; photostat (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Letter of Lewis Cass to Mason, July 7, 1832 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      (brief letter)
    - Lewis Cass to Stevens T. Mason, Washington, October 26, 1832; 3 pages (Box 1, Folder 3)
      (marked "Private." The letter was written in response to letter of Mason's apparently complaining of delay re decision on federal payment of Michigan militia. Cass attempts to salve Mason's feelings and gives a word or two of personal advice)
    - Lewis Cass to Governor George B. Porter "or in his absence Stevens T. Mason Secretary of Michigan," Washington, October 26, 1832 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      (Written in reply to Porter's [probably] letter of the 24th. Cass says that the Michigan militia recently called up to meet Indian hostilities "will...be recognized as entitled to pay from the United States.")
    - Lewis Cass to Stevens T. Mason, Washington, October 20, 1834; 3 pages (Box 1, Folder 3)
      (marked "Private." The letter concerns payment of federal funds to Michigan and the appointment of Mr. Dickerson as factor in Green Bay)
    - Lewis Cass to Stevens T. Mason, Washington, November 4, 1834 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      (marked "Private." Interesting comments by Cass on President Andrew Jackson's plan to appoint a new governor in Michigan)
  - February-March 1835
    - Stevens T. Mason to John Forsyth, United States Secretary of State, Detroit, February 20, 1835; 9 pages (Box 1, Folder 4)
      (Letter concerns Michigan's boundary dispute with Ohio. It sets forth Michigan's claims against Ohio and warns of serious consequences from the actions of Ohio Governor Lucas)
    - Stevens T. Mason to General Joseph Brown, Detroit, February 28, 1835; 3 pages (Box 1, Folder 4)
      (Mason instructs Brown to be firm in his attitude toward inhabitants of the disputed territory.)
    - Circular from the Executive office in Detroit, March 2, 1835 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      (Orders to brigade commanders to prepare for service to Michigan under General Joseph Brown's command)
    - Stevens T. Mason to Secretary John Forsyth, Detroit, March 6, 1835; 2 pages (Box 1, Folder 4)
      (Mason notes the action of Ohio to extend jurisdiction over disputed territory and requests federal government's views on the dispute "before the parties in controversy shall proceed to extremities.")
    - Stevens T. Mason to General Joseph W. Brown, Detroit, March 17, 1835; 3 pages (Box 1, Folder 4)
      (In reply to Brown's letter, Mason urges caution and suggests strategy for dealing with Ohio's forthcoming attempt to exercise civil functions in the disputed territory. Mason suggests plan to arrest Ohio Governor Lucas after crossing into the disputed territory.)
    - Stevens T. Mason to President Andrew Jackson, Detroit, March 21, 1835; 11 pages (Box 1, Folder 4)
      (Mason asks the President to protect Michigan from "the encroachments and usurpations of a powerful neighboring state." He details the activities of Ohio and its governor in the controversy. Mason suggests that U.S. troops proceed to Toledo to keep the peace in that quarter.)
    - Stevens T. Mason to Secretary John Forsyth, Detroit, March 23, 1835; 4 pages (Box 1, Folder 4)
      (Letter written in reply to a letter of Forsyth's of March 14th. Mason regrets the President's failure to communicate his wishes (beyond urging forbearance) to Mason in the controversy with Ohio.)
    - Stevens T. Mason to Secretary John Forsyth, Detroit, March 27, 1835; 5 pages (Box 1, Folder 4)
      (Letter written in reply to a letter of the 17th from Forsyth. Mason assures Forsyth that Michigan will not hastily resort to force, but again urges that the President make known his views on the controversy.)
  - April 1-15, 1835
    - Stevens T. Mason to Secretary Forsyth, Monroe, April 2, 1835; 6 pages (Box 1, Folder 5)
      (Mason says public opinion in Michigan would not accept submission to Ohio, and that if Ohio employs force, Michigan might respond in kind.)
    - Stevens T. Mason to Governor Lucas of Ohio, Monroe, April 2, 1835; 7 pages (Box 1, Folder 5)
      (Mason warns Lucas that Michigan will not surrender any of the disputed territory "until the competent tribunal shall have decided the question in controversy," but expresses hope that the dispute will be settled to the satisfaction of both sides.)
    - Richard Rush and Benjamin C. Howard to Mason, Monroe, April 10, 1835; 5 pages photostat (Box 1, Folder 5)
      (Letter urges moderation on the part of both Mason and the Ohio authorities with respect to border dispute)
    - Stevens T. Mason to Mssrs. Howard and Rush, Commissioners of the President, Monroe, April 10, 1835; 16 pages (Box 1, Folder 5)
      (Mason puts forth Michigan's side of the controversy in some detail, and again asserts Michigan's intention to defend its position.)
    - Richard Rush and Benjamin C. Howard to Stevens T. Mason, Toledo, April 14, 1835; 2 pages photostat (Box 1, Folder 5)
      (Letter urging that force not be used by Mason against the Ohio authorities.)
  - April 16-30, 1835
    - Stevens T. Mason to Mssrs. Howard and Rush, Detroit, April 18, 1835; 5 pages (Box 1, Folder 6)
      (Mason regrets that he cannot more fully co-operate with the two United States Commissioners.)
    - Stevens T. Mason to Lewis Cass, Tecumseh, April 25, 1835; 3 pages (Box 1, Folder 6)
      (Mason informs Cass that Ohio has begun running its claimed boundary line, and he requests immediate federal action to protect "the territory and jurisdiction of the United States.")
    - Stevens T. Mason to Secretary Forsyth, Detroit, April 29, 1835; 4 pages (Box 1, Folder 6)
      (Mason urges the Federal government to cease acting merely as mediator and assert the sovereignty of the United States over the disputed territory.)
  - May-December 1835
    - Lewis Cass to Stevens T. Mason, "Confidential," Washington, May 1, 1835; 3 pages (Box 1, Folder 7)
      (Cass asks Mason to understand that as a member of the President's cabinet he cannot express his true sentiments as freely as he would like in regard to the dispute between Ohio and his own state of Michigan. He comments upon Jackson's fairness and says that Jackson will act with a "single eye to his duty.")
    - Stevens T. Mason to Commissioners Rush and Howard, Monroe, May 1, 1835; 2 pages (Box 1, Folder 7)
      (Mason expresses willingness of Michigan to cooperate with the proper courts in resolving the controversy with Ohio.)
    - Stevens T. Mason to Secretary Forsyth, Monroe, May 2, 1835 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      (Mason says he is enclosing a copy of his letter to the Commissioners of May 1.)
    - Stevens T. Mason to U.S. Commissioners, Monroe, May 3, 1835 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      (Mason refuses to consider any solution "short of an exclusive jurisdiction" over the disputed territory.)
    - Lewis Cass to Stevens T. Mason, Washington, May 9, 1835; 7 pages original and typescript (Box 1, Folder 7)
      (Cass admits his own belief that Michigan's claims are correct, but expresses concern lest possible "civil war" erupt between Michigan and Ohio. He says Jackson hopes conflict will be resolved without his interference beyond "advice and remonstrance." Cass advises Mason to "temper the firmness of the community with a due show of moderation.")
    - Stevens T. Mason to Secretary Forsyth, Detroit, July 11, 1835; 6 pages (Box 1, Folder 7)
      (Mason says he has convened the Legislature for August 17th and will submit the compromise proposition to the members. Mason recites his determination to remember the rights of the "high minded and patriotic people" of Michigan.)
    - Lewis Cass to Stevens T. Mason, Detroit, July 11, 1835; 2 pages (Box 1, Folder 7)
      (Cass offers to come to Monroe if Mason thinks it would be helpful in averting a "collision")
    - Stevens T. Mason to Secretary Forsyth, Monroe, July 17, 1835; 3 pages; 2 copies (Box 1, Folder 7)
      (Mason says he is enclosing affidavits pertaining to the wounding of the sheriff in Toledo and urges action lest delay result in further violence.)
    - Extract of a letter from Secretary Forsyth to Lewis Cass, Washington, July 22, 1835; 4 pages (Box 1, Folder 7)
      (Forsyth criticizes Mason for not accepting the recommendations of the President in bringing about a temporary arrangement pending final solution of the boundary dispute.)
    - Lewis Cass to Stevens T. Mason, Washington, August 11, 1835; 3 pages (Box 1, Folder 7)
      (Cass warns Mason that his failure to coincide with Jackson's policies may bring about his removal by the President.)
    - Lewis Cass to Mason, August 16, 1835; typescript (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Stevens T. Mason to Secretary Forsyth, Detroit, August 21, 1835; 2 pages (Box 1, Folder 7)
      (Mason says Michigan will resist by force any attempt by Ohio to exercise jurisdiction.)
  - 1838
    - Unsigned note to Mason, dated New York City, May 4, 1838; 2 pages photostat (Box 1, Folder 8)
      (Refers to invitation of a "Judge McGruder" for Mason to visit him on his way through Baltimore.)
    - Stevens T. Mason to Professor Asa Gray, New York, October 31, 1838; 4 pages photostat plus copy of original (Box 1, Folder 8)
      (Mason encloses a copy of a letter giving instructions as to the expenditure of funds ($6500) appropriated by the Legislature to Professor Gray for his trip to Europe.)
    - Acting Secretary of State Aaron Vail to Stevens T. Mason, Washington, November 5, 1838 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      (Marked "Confidential," Secretary Vail encloses a copy of letter from British minister to the United States to the State Department pertaining to threatened invasion of Canada by insurgents based in the United States. Secretary Vail calls attention to that portion of the letter warning of possible attack on state arsenals.)
  - 1842
    - [Firm of] Hale and Harding to Mason, Detroit, March 23, 1842; 2 pages photostat (Box 1, Folder 9)
      (Letter refers to lands owned by Col. George W. Owens and V. Ellsworth.)
    - George W. Owens to Stevens T. Mason, Savannah, May 4, 1842; 2 pages photostat (Box 1, Folder 9)
      (Letter deals with personal financial matters.)
    - I. Allen B. to Albert W. Parris, Lancaster, Wisconsin Territory, June 14, 1842; photostat (Box 1, Folder 9)
      (One page letter concerning land taxes.)
    - Albert W. Parrish to Stevens T. Mason, Madison, Wisconsin Territory, June 22, 1842; photostat (Box 1, Folder 9)
      (Two page letter concerning land taxes.)
    - R.W. Owens to Stevens T. Mason, Savannah, July 27, 1842; photostat (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Stevens T. Mason to Albert W. Parrish, New York City, August 1, 1842; photostat (Box 1, Folder 9)
      (One page letter concerning land taxes)
  - Undated
    - Undated letter, 1836 or 1840 written in pencil by Mason to certain political leaders in Virginia concerning presidential contest between Harrison and Van Buren, 9 pages (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Other papers
  - Notice of election to membership in Michigan Historical Society (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Essay "Sincerity" by Emily Mason (S. T. Mason's sister); also letter (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Unsigned draft of defense counsel's pleas before a court (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous papers (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous photostats (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Newspaper clippings (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Photographs (Box 1)
    Photographs in the Mason papers include prints (ca. 1880s) of a portrait of Mason's sister, Emily Virginia Mason, Mason's grave in New York City, and Mason's home in Detroit, Michigan; portrait of Mason's daughter, Dorothea Mason Wright; photograph of painting of Mason (ca. 1830s); and photographs of statue of Mason.
  - "Artistides" to Augustus S. Porter, "Knight of Black Rock," or, undated 1831; 1832; 11 pages (Box 2, Folder 17)
    (letter, very critical of Porter, refers to his "unmanly and disgraceful conduct in the affair with the editor of the Courier")
  - Miscellaneous commissions signed by Mason; land patent and related documents, 1800 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Addresses and messages to the Legislature, etc.
  - To the Legislative Council, November 19, 1834; 5 pages (Box 2, Folder 19)
    (re election of delegates to form a constitution for Michigan and the effect of such action upon the border dispute with Ohio.)
  - Message to the Legislature, February 1, 1836 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Inaugural address, January 2, 1838 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    (2 drafts)
  - Message to the Legislature, March 8, 1838; 3 pages (Box 2, Folder 22)
    (Governor recommends a loan to the University of Michigan.)
  - Message to the Senate, March 22, 1838; 2 pages (Box 2, Folder 23)
    (Governor recommends creation of a state board of loan commissioners.)
  - Annual message to the Legislature, January 7, 1839 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Address to the "free and independent electors of the State of Michigan", circa 1840; 31 pages (Box 2, Folder 25)
    (Address presents Mason's [i.e. Democratic party's] point of view concerning recent Michigan politics.)
  - Address to unidentified association regarding history of the northwest, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)